<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://cwrc.ca/schemas/cwrc_tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://cwrc.ca/templates/css/tei-DToC.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en-CA" level="m" type="main">Regenerations</title>
                <title xml:lang="en-CA" level="m" type="sub">Canadian Women's Writing</title>
                <title xml:lang="fr-CA" level="m" type="main">Régénérations</title>
                <title xml:lang="fr-CA" level="m" type="sub">Écriture des femmes au Canada</title>
                <editor role="editor">
                    <forename>Marrie</forename>
                    <forename>Carrière</forename>
                </editor>
                <editor role="editor">
                    <forename>Patricia</forename>
                    <surname>Demers</surname>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <forename>Susan</forename>
                    <surname>Brown</surname>
                </principal>
                <editor role="markup_editor">
                    <forename>Mihaela</forename>
                    <forename>Ilovan</forename>
                </editor>
                <editor role="markup_editor">
                    <forename>Ruth</forename>
                    <surname>Knechtel</surname>
                </editor>
                <funder>
                    <orgName>University of Alberta Libraries</orgName>
                </funder>
                <funder>
                    <orgName>Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada</orgName>
                </funder>
                <sponsor><orgName xml:lang="en-CA">Canadian Literature Centre</orgName>/<orgName xml:lang="fr-CA">Centre de littérature canadienne</orgName></sponsor>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Implementing New Knowledge Environments</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Text Mining and Visualization for Literary History</orgName>
                </sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Dynamic Table of Contexts edition</edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Interface design lead:</resp>
                    <name role="designer">
                        <forename>Stan</forename>
                        <surname>Ruecker</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Interface development lead:</resp>
                    <name role="programmer">
                        <forename>Stéfan</forename>
                        <surname>Sinclair</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Researcher: </resp>
                    <name role="researcher">
                        <forename>Brent</forename>
                        <surname>Nelson</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Designers: </resp>
                    <name role="designer">
                        <forename>Jennifer</forename>
                        <surname>Windsor</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name role="designer">
                        <forename>Milena</forename>
                        <surname>Radzikowska</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Publishing director: </resp>
                    <name role="publishing_director">
                        <forename>Linda</forename>
                        <surname>Cameron</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Copy editors and proofreaders: </resp>
                    <name role="proofreader">
                        <forename>Joanne</forename>
                        <surname>Muzak</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name role="proofreader">
                        <forename>Anna</forename>
                        <surname>Oliver</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Designer - cover and text: </resp>
                    <name role="book_designer">
                        <forename>Marvin</forename>
                        <surname>Harder</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Digital coordinator: </resp>
                    <name role="contributor">
                        <forename>Duncan</forename>
                        <surname>Turner</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Indexers: </resp>
                    <name role="contributor">
                        <forename>Judy</forename>
                        <surname>Dunlop</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name><forename>François</forename> Trahan</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Production manager: </resp>
                    <name role="book_producer">
                        <forename>MaryLou</forename>
                        <surname>Roy</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Developer: </resp>
                    <name role="programmer">
                        <forename>Andrew</forename>
                        <surname>Macdonald</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by:</resp>
                    <name role="markup_editor">
                        <forename>Nadine</forename>
                        <surname>Adelaar</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name role="markup_editor">
                        <forename>Olga</forename>
                        <surname>Ivanova</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name role="markup_editor">
                        <forename>Samantha</forename>
                        <surname>Fitzner</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name role="markup_editor">
                        <forename>Kaarina</forename>
                        <surname>Mikalson</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>

            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName role="publisher">University of Alberta Press</orgName>
                    <address> 
                        <addrLine>Ring House 2</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Edmonton, Alberta, Canada   T6G 2E1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>www.uap.ualberta.ca</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName role="publisher">Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory</orgName>
                    <address><addrLine>www.cwrc.ca</addrLine></address>
                </publisher>
                <idno type="ISBN">ISBN: 978-1-55195-345-8</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2015 The University of Alberta Press</p>
                    <p>All rights reserved. No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means (electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording, or otherwise) without prior written consent. Contact the University of Alberta Press for further details.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p></p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note></note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="fr-CA">French</language>
                <language ident="en-CA">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <byline></byline>
                <item></item>
                <index>
                    <term></term>
                </index>
                <byline></byline>
                <index>
                    <term></term>
                </index>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            
            
            
            <div type="part">
                
                
                
                <div type="chapter" xml:lang="en-CA">
                    <head><title level="a">Common Measure</title></head>
                    <byline><hi rend="italic"><q>Folk Poetry</q></hi> and the Scandal of Canadian Literature</byline>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/110237888" cert="high">Gary Kelly</persName>
                    </docAuthor>
                    <p xml:id="p817">
                        <ref target="#nationality_issue">What <ref target="#theme_or_topic">Canadian literature</ref> publishes and studies, most Canadians seldom read, unless for school or college. What most Canadians read and write, Canadian literature seldom studies, and most such studies come from outside Canadian literature. <ref target="#genre_poetry">An example is <ref target="#theme_or_topic">study of <q>folk poetry</q></ref> (<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/103982524" cert="high" sameAs="Roger deV Renwick">Renwick</persName>, <persName sameAs="Pauline Greenhill" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/18627631">Greenhill</persName>), or poetry written by people of all kinds about their lives and concerns, for themselves, family, and friends, perhaps published with a church magazine, local newspaper, or <q>vanity press,</q> reflecting on and part of their creation of everyday life, of what we call <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6251999">Canada</placeName>.</ref></ref>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="p818">One such poet was LJ (identity withheld in deference to family). <ref target="#archival_location">The following account comes from her children, who hold her writings, which comprise several plastic covered notebooks of fair copies of poems, some prose journals, and a few single-sheet poems.</ref> The texts are transcribed here as found. LJ’s life and writings illustrate what Canadian literature, as their reading and writing, likely is for most Canadians. Born in <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6169276">Trout Creek, Ontario</placeName> in <date cert="high" when="1921">1921</date>, LJ lived most of her life in <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/6167865" cert="high">Toronto</placeName> and the last decade in <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6173331">Vancouver</placeName>, where she died in <date cert="high" when="1978">1978</date>. <ref target="#class_issue">Her life had the vicissitudes often experienced by <q>ordinary</q> people of her class and generation, including <ref target="#education">early withdrawal from formal education for financial reasons, a later turn to evening-school and correspondence courses, and engagement in self-education and self-expression.</ref></ref> Lived partly in what culture critics condescendingly call <q>tabloidia,</q> LJ’s experience included serious illness, family breakup, failed relationships, a child out of wedlock, frequent changes of residence, <ref target="#violence">sexual harassment, domestic violence (including murder of a relative)</ref>, <ref target="#economics">low-quality dangerous housing, and poorly paid jobs.</ref> Like most, LJ followed the news and related her life to its representations of the world. Like most, LJ enjoyed popular arts, such as social dance, movies, radio, television, the occasional theatre play or musical, clothes-making, paint-by-numbers, and her writing. She drank little, never smoked, seldom swore, had few love relationships, <ref target="#religion">attended various churches intermittently</ref>, and had several close women friends. To understand her experience and world, she resorted to tea leaf reading, astrology, the Ouija board, and playing card prophecies; to apt traditional proverbs or self-made maxims; and to writing. Exemplifying what <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/108178108" sameAs="Anthony Giddens">Giddens</persName> describes as one of the <q>consequences of modernity,</q> her reading and writing participated in, reflected on, and expressed an ongoing remaking of herself and her life in relation to everyday local, national, and global issues of the day.</p>
                    <p xml:id="p819">She drew her formal repertory and diction from several sources that resonated with her interests. Those she recalled most fondly were from childhood and school (see <persName cert="high" sameAs="Catherine Robson" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/117385338">Robson</persName>). <ref target="#intertextuality">She often recited <persName sameAs="William Wordsworth" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35723133">Wordsworth</persName>’s <title level="a">The Solitary Reaper.</title> This poem’s idea of the lowly and transient rendered permanent and inspiring, or heart-borne, likely shaped LJ’s idea of what poetry should be, and she often used this verse form. Another favourite was <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95207986" sameAs="Robert Louis Stevenson">Stevenson</persName>’s <title level="m">A Child’s Garden of Verses</title>; seriously ill when young, she often recited <title level="a">The Land of Counterpane,</title> where a child creates an imaginary world. Memorized from the same volume was <title level="a">My Shadow.</title> <ref target="#theme_or_topic">This poem’s theme of companionship with oneself, involuntary but empowering, was a recurring theme in LJ’s poetry.</ref></ref></p>
                    <p xml:id="p820">
                        <ref target="#genre_music">Formal and thematic models also came from her favourite popular songs, which, like most people, she used to understand both feelingly and critically her own experience, especially emotions and relationships (see <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/45965317" cert="high" sameAs="Susan D. Crafts">Crafts</persName>, <persName>Cavicchi</persName>, and <persName>Keil</persName>). For example, <title level="a">Mr. Wonderful,</title> title song of the <date cert="high" when="1956">1956</date> Broadway musical starring <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/54184962">Sammy Davis Jr.</persName> (one of LJ’s favourite artists along with <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12394764" cert="high">Bing Crosby</persName> and <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/34642861">Nat King Cole</persName>), addresses the mystery of attraction: <q type="block"><lg type="stanza"> <l>Why this feeling? Why this glow?</l> <l>Why the thrill when you say Hello?</l> <l>It’s a strange and tender magic you do</l> <l>Mister Wonderful, that’s you.</l> </lg>(<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/85378455" cert="high" sameAs="Jerry Bock">Bock</persName>, <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35790321" sameAs="Lawrence Holofcener">Holofcener</persName>, and <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100400827" cert="high" sameAs="George David Weiss">Weiss</persName>)</q> Another favourite, <title level="a">Smoke Gets in Your Eyes,</title> was best known from the <date cert="high" when="1935">1935</date> film <title level="m">Roberta</title>, featuring <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9888263">Fred Astaire</persName> and <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/114114463" cert="high">Ginger Rogers</persName>. It addresses betrayal and loss. Her attachment for this song seems related to her husband’s infidelity and abandonment of her soon after the birth of their child. A later favourite, the <date cert="high" when="1956">1956</date> <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/64913773">Jerry Vale</persName> hit, <title level="a">You Don’t Know Me,</title> seems to reflect on her love for her husband. It begins: <q type="block"><lg type="stanza"> <l>You give your hand to me</l> <l>And then you say hello</l> <l>I can hardly speak</l> <l>My heart is beating so</l> <l>And anyone can tell</l> <l>You think you know me well</l> <l>But you don’t know me.</l> </lg> (<persName sameAs="Cindy Walker" ref=" http://viaf.org/viaf/9107221" cert="high">Walker</persName> and <persName sameAs="Eddy Arnold" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32182471">Arnold</persName>)</q> <ref target="#intertextuality">For many people, a personal memory archive of popular song, like a scrapbook of cuttings and ephemera, was literature in and for everyday life.</ref></ref>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="p821"> <ref target="#economics">LJ was a reader but, unable to afford books, owned few apart from the highly popular Reader’s Digest condensed books, hand-me-downs from her father’s second wife, also a reader.</ref> Though LJ’s poetry and life resemble those of bestselling Canadian <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52059451" cert="high">Edna Jaques</persName> from an earlier generation, there is no evidence LJ encountered Jaques’s poetry or distinguished it from other newspaper and magazine <q>folk poetry.</q> In the <date cert="low" from="1950" to="1959">1950s</date>, LJ bought a battered second-hand family Bible, had it cheaply rebound, recorded her family tree there, and at times read daily in it, a symbol of social continuity and stability she aspired to rather than experienced. She owned a cookbook, seldom opened, also symbolic: work fatigue left energy for cooking little beyond fried basics. <ref target="#health_issue">In the 1970s, suffering chronic heart disease but leery of the public health care introduced a decade earlier, she acquired popular health books along with various nostrums.</ref> She followed the news, subscribing at times to the populist Canadian <title level="j">Liberty</title> magazine and <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6167865">Toronto</placeName> <title level="j">Telegram</title> newspaper. <ref target="#class_issue">She didn’t use public libraries, perhaps like many feeling that, with museums and galleries, they were not for people like her.</ref> Like most, she enjoyed the play of everyday language, humorously twisting common words, phrases, and names. <ref target="#non-book_media">She got her first television set, a defective castoff, in the <date cert="low" from="1955" to="1959">late 1950s</date>; her favourite programs, as with most North Americans then, were <title level="m">I Love Lucy</title> and <title level="m">The Lawrence Welk Show</title> . In the <date from="1960" to="1969" cert="low">1960s</date>, like millions of others she took up paint-by-numbers.</ref> </p>
                    <p xml:id="p822">
                        <ref target="#genre_poetry">She seldom showed her writing but made no secret of it and referred to it proudly as <q>My poetry.</q> What survives resembles her favourite poetry of childhood and school and popular songs of youth and adulthood. This poetry was unlike the modernist poetry produced by Canadian and similar literatures in LJ’s lifetime, which proclaimed <q>difficulty</q> and <q>experiment</q> and later developed a corresponding specialist academic critical discourse, both in flight from the vulgar and mass culture and designed to form literary vanguards, coteries, and professional elites (<persName>Longabucco</persName>) and restrict access to them. <ref target="#textual_strategies">The poetry LJ drew on purposefully reworked the historic popular poetic idiom comprising common measure and its variants and a <q>purified</q> or selected vernacular, the same appropriated by <persName sameAs="William Worsworth" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35723133">Wordsworth</persName></ref> (taking his lead from contemporary women poets) for a poetic revolution that he meant to effect a national cultural uplifting. In content, LJ’s poems, like the majority of personal lyric poetry of the past two centuries, was from her own life and usually <q>occasional,</q> or prompted by specific and specified events.</ref>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="p823"><ref target="#manuscript_history">Most of LJ’s surviving poems are dated from the <date cert="low" from="1970" to="1979">1970s</date> but include a few earlier ones apparently copied from memory: earlier work was likely lost in her many moves across city and country.</ref> The earliest, dated <q><date cert="medium" when="1938">Approx 1938</date>,</q> is a jingle, <title level="a">Ivory Soap,</title> likely inspired by magazine and radio contests of the time. It opens: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>I like gentle Ivory soap</l> <l>For every cleaning purpose</l> <l>It gets right in and digs out dirt</l> <l>Then leaves a shining surface.</l> </lg> </q> Another, <title level="a">My Dream, </title>dated <q><date when="1940-12" cert="high">Dec. 1940</date></q> (she was nineteen) follows popular love songs in sentiment and phrasing. It may have expressed early love for her future husband: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>What makes me think of you all through the day?</l> <l>In loneliness it’s you I can’t forget.</l> <l>…</l> <l>To feel your tender hand in mine</l> <l>is one desire</l> <l>That no one knows.</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l>All this means much to me, far more</l> <l>Than human tongue can tell.</l> <l>In life I am quite satisfied to have but you</l> <l>To love so well.</l> </lg> </q> <ref target="#genre_music">In popular song and grand opera, such lyrics are animated by music, and LJ may have had a tune in mind. Further, personal appropriation of phrases from popular song validates private feelings.</ref> This poem may also have been part of a verse exchange: with it LJ kept a signed poem from her future husband, entitled <title level="a">My Girl.</title></p>
                    <p xml:id="p824">The act of writing structures experience critically: after her failed marriage and the birth of a child by another man, came this, dated <date cert="high" when="1950">1950</date>: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>I have a little stream,</l> <l>I made it through the years,</l> <l>For every little drop of water</l> <l>Used to be my tears.</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l>Some were tears of joy</l> <l>And some were tears of sorrow</l> <l>And some were tears I cried inside</l> <l>For what might come to-morrow.</l> </lg></q> <ref target="#genre_poetry">As often in <q>folk poetry,</q> light rhythm and tone counterbalance strong feeling.</ref> </p>
                    <p xml:id="p825"><ref target="#theme_or_topic">Perhaps because of her circumstances, motherhood as resistance and struggle formed a major element in LJ’s poetized self-identity.</ref> <title level="a">Mother Love,</title> dated <date when="1950" cert="high">1950</date>, expresses feelings for her <q>love-child</q>: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>I have a lovely little girl,</l> <l>Her hair is blonde with not much curl</l> <l>But every little lock of hair</l> <l>Has a heart string tied up there…</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l>She has the biggest soft-brown eyes.</l> <l>Her kisses fill me full of sighs</l> <l>Then little feet take her away</l> <l>And leave me empty all the day.</l> </lg> </q> <ref target="#intertextuality">The poem, especially the close, echoes <persName cert="high" sameAs="Robert Louis Stevenson" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95207986">Stevenson</persName>’s <title level="a">Land of Counterpane,</title> but filled with loss rather than the child <q>giant’s</q>power in Stevenson’s poem. <ref target="#textual_strategies">Again, frames used by popular poets and song writers were adapted to personal experience and expression, asserting the personal in a public and <ref target="#theme_or_topic">popular discourse and culture</ref>, here validating what would have been widely condemned at the time as an illicit love and its consequence.</ref></ref></p>
                    <p xml:id="p826">Some years after both children had left home, she wrote this, dated <date when="1974-12-07" cert="high">December 7, 1974</date>, about her first child, whom well-educated friends of her husband had wanted to adopt after he had left her, to give the child an <q>appropriate</q> education and upbringing: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>God gave to me a son,</l> <l>He chose me as a mother,</l> <l>If I was good enough for God</l> <l>Why can’t I please my brother?</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l>I loved him from the start</l> <l>This child so full of beauty,</l> <l>No matter where the future led</l> <l>To raise him was my duty…</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l>And now I’m far away.</l> <l>I’ve left those years behind me.</l> <l>My son (now a full grown man)</l> <l>Could what may have been, have changed thee?</l> </lg> </q> <ref target="#class_issue">The struggles of lone parenthood merged with struggles and frustrations of everyday working-poor life, as in <title level="a">Waiting,</title> dated <date cert="high" when="1951">1951</date>: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>Here I am a waiting</l> <l>In another line.</l> <l>Seems as though I’m doing this</l> <l>Nearly all the time.</l> <l>For every time I pay a bill</l> <l>It always seems to be</l> <l>That half a dozen other folk</l> <l>Are just ahead of me.</l> </lg> </q></ref><ref target="#intertextuality">This recalls the sound and shape of <persName cert="high" sameAs="Robert Louis Stevenson" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95207986">Stevenson</persName>’s <title level="a">My Shadow,</title> but its use of vernacular also shoulders such <q>literary</q> poetry as that of American modernist <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/66611608">Lorine Niedecker</persName></ref>. A continuation about waiting for buses is dated <date cert="high" when="1975-11-09">November 9, 1975</date>, twenty-four years later. LJ often re-opened a poem to update it with the daily living that it engaged with.</p>
                    <p xml:id="p827"><ref target="#theme_or_topic">Her poems about ecology and the environment converge a public political concern emerging in the <date cert="low" from="1970" to="1979">1970s</date> with a lifelong personal concern for what she saw as the crowds, dirt, and confusion of the city—or the parts of cities she could afford to live in</ref>. <title level="a">Waste</title> is dated <date cert="high" when="1975-10-31">October 31, 1975</date>, and begins: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>We like to turn the tap on</l> <l>And wash the waste away;</l> <l>The particles of food</l> <l>And dirt from children’s play.</l> <l>All these things go down the drain</l> <l>With water clear and fresh.</l> <l>But where do they land up?</l> <l>Do they only make a mess?</l> </lg> </q> The poem calls for solutions: <q> <lg type="stanza"> <l>Surely we can think ahead</l> <l>And figure out a theme</l> <l>So that waste goes back again</l> <l>To aid in Nature’s scheme.…</l> <l>And maybe we should go again</l> <l>To houses on the hill</l> <l>So lakes and rivers will be clean</l> <l>And with fish again will fill[.]</l> </lg> </q> A countering group of poems concerns small, free, or cheap daily pleasures such as the beach, a cup of tea, a warm bath, a warm bed. <title level="a">See the Sea,</title> dated <q>Wed <date when="1975-03-05" cert="high">March 5, 1975</date>,</q> probably refers to <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5993124">Kitsilano beach, Vancouver</placeName>: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>Water is the thing to see</l> <l>For without it there couldn’t be</l> <l>Ships to sail, fish to swim,</l> <l>A place of peace for you and me…</l> </lg> </q> A day later she added: <q> <lg type="stanza"> <l>A rainbow flashed across the foam</l> <l>As sunshine on the beaches shone.</l> <l>It warmed us. We were refreshed</l> <l>From salty breezes that were blown.</l> </lg> </q> <ref target="#close_reading">Though LJ’s poems often emphasized her solitariness, here, as in many other poems, there is an imagined and inclusive company of <q>we</q> and an imaginary companion <q>you.</q> Simple comforts are celebrated in several pieces, such as <title level="a">A Cup-a,</title> dated <date cert="high" when="1974-12-07">December 7, 1974</date>: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>When you’re having troubles</l> <l>And you don’t know what to do</l> <l>Sit down and have a cup-a</l> <l>And think your problems through.</l> </lg> </q></ref> <ref target="#genre_poetry">Resembling an advertising jingle or greeting card rhyme, this poem illustrates the productive dialogue between personal poetry and commercial verse forms</ref>. </p>
                    <p xml:id="p828">Like many other poets, she also wrote about the problems and pleasures of writing. When troubled at night she found that writing soothed her for sleep: a number of poems have dates such as <q>Midnight</q> or <q>4 a.m.</q> <title level="a">The Poetry of My Delight,</title> dated <date when="1972-02" cert="high">February 1972</date>, associates the struggle of living with the struggle of writing: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>At six a.m. I wake and lie</l> <l>And cannot sleep and wonder why</l> <l>As many thoughts go flying by</l> <l> Much disturbed am I.</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l>At seven o’clock I rise and write</l> <l>The poetry of my delight</l> <l>Because I cannot sleep to-night</l> <l>For something isn’t right.</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l> Many thoughts run through my head</l> <l>Of things I’ve done and things I’ve read</l> <l>But thoughts of things that should be said</l> <l>Were heavier than lead.</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l>The words of life come from within</l> <l>And flow like magic when they begin</l> <l>But if we dare to capture them</l> <l> Outside forces intervene…</l> </lg> </q></p>
                    <p xml:id="p829"><ref target="#education">By the <date cert="low" from="1970" to="1979">1970s</date>, both her children had got through university thanks to summer jobs, living at home, and the recently instituted <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6251999">Canada</placeName> student loan program. <ref target="#class_issue">LJ’s poem <title level="a">Wealth of Knowledge,</title> dated <date cert="high" when="1975-02-06">February 6, 1975</date>, shows that, whatever its benefits, education, as with many working-class families, separated her—and her writing—from her children and their world of knowledge, including <q>Canadian literature</q></ref></ref>: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>There is a book shelf on my wall</l> <l>That’s filled with books both large and small</l> <l>But I have not yet read them all</l> <l>For I am known to stall.</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l>The experiences of life that I have led</l> <l> All go up into my head</l> <l>But one day they may be read</l> <l>After, or before I’m dead…</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l> We each must express in our own way</l> <l>The things that have happened from day to day.</l> <l> Some folks the piano play</l> <l>And some pictures paint to relate what they may.</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l> What I enjoy is to write a rhyme</l> <l>With music there upon the line,</l> <l>Sometimes at a peculiar time</l> <l>At night, or when solitude is mine…</l> </lg> </q> Perhaps dissatisfied with her psychologistic closure, four days later (<date when="1975-02-10" cert="high">February 10</date>) she added a stanza of spiritually questioning: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>Does it not then seem to be</l> <l>That more than one life is lived by me</l> <l>And the rest of mankind so that we</l> <l>Experiences may teach what we cannot see?</l> </lg> </q></p>
                    <p xml:id="p830">Overall, her concern in these <date cert="low" from="1970" to="1979">1970s</date> poems, even when dealing with large issues such as pollution, social conflict, or the economy, was with small everyday challenges and pleasures, overcoming or arranging, which, like writing a poem, engaged the creativity that constitutes everyday living, making a life from available materials. Here, for example, is <title level="a">The Worker,</title> dated <date when="1975-01-28" cert="high">January 28, 1975</date>, when she was at <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/157027150">Canada Post</orgName>: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>I work part time at a job that I enjoy.</l> <l>I’ve seen mistakes when a man becomes a boy</l> <l>When the pressures of a job makes someone lose his senses</l> <l>And the damage that creates is really quite tremendous.</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l>We study and we try hard to make their program function,</l> <l>A machine can only do so much and then it starts a munching.</l> <l>It munches on the letters and it spits out all the stamps</l> <l>Or pens that sometimes come inside are chewed up, then it jams.</l> </lg> <lg type="stanza"> <l>We mostly pull together as a group of willing workers.</l> <l>Still no matter where you work there will always be the shirkers.</l> <l>The job pays well. I really can’t complain.</l> <l>Yet industry does make mistakes and who or what’s to blame.</l> </lg> </q> A fourth stanza is dated <date cert="high" when="1975-02-09">February 9, 1975</date>: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>We climb up the mechanical stairs ’cause they’re not operating,</l> <l>And pick up parcels from the floor when the round table can’t contain them.</l> <l>For ten minutes each evening, we have no time to wait</l> <l>Up in our cafeteria, where we vie for coffee and cake.</l> </lg> </q> <ref target="#politics">A final stanza is dated <date when="1975-11-06" cert="high">November 6, 1975</date>: <q type="block"> <lg type="stanza"> <l>We picket the post office when our members are on strike</l> <l>A few come in the evening or in the black of night.</l> <l>Because I am a worker it seems the thing to do.</l> <l>If you are a worker won’t you come and picket too?</l> </lg> </q></ref></p>
                    <p xml:id="p831">Here is writing used as most people use it, for its most important purpose—as ethnomethodologists (<persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/108536033" sameAs="Harold Garfinkel">Garfinkel</persName>, <persName sameAs="Alec McHoul" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/2537401" cert="high">McHoul</persName>) would insist—creating everyday life day by day. <ref target="#nationality_issue">Here is Canadian literature in the fullest sense, the literature of most Canadians, creating their own imaginary and reality, for themselves.</ref></p>
                    <p xml:id="p832">
                        <ref target="#nationality_issue">
                            <ref target="#critique_of_canon">Since the Romantic era, <q>national</q> literatures have been fabricated to depreciate, marginalize, and displace such people’s literatures in the interests of coalitions of professional, business, political, and social elites who strive to impose their imaginary and reality as <q>national</q> (<persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12428950" sameAs="Martha Woodmansee">Woodmansee</persName>). Certain discursive and disciplinary practices have been taught in schools and colleges, professionalized in academia, funded by the state, and deployed in cultural media to promote elites’ <q>national</q> literature at the expense of the people’s.</ref>
                        </ref>
                        <ref target="#methodology">
                            <ref target="#intellectual_history">Despite policy-driven cultural pluralization and poststructuralist theorizing of recent decades, prominent among these practices remain literarism, or the notion that <q>literary value</q> or <q>quality</q> inheres in texts and that it is what <q>matters</q> about them; textism, or the notion that meanings inhere in texts; and telepathism, or the notion that meanings are encoded by authors in texts and decoded and internalized by readers. Texto-telepathism has been around for centuries in various forms, but its most influential version today is the Franco-American neo-Hegelianism traceable to <persName sameAs="György Lukács" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/46764285">Lukács</persName>’s <date cert="high" when="1923">1923</date> argument that mass culture <q>commodities</q> <q>massify</q> their <q>consumers.</q> This view was adapted and passed on by many across <placeName>Europe</placeName> and the Americas through the twentieth century, including such often cited figures as <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/13017" sameAs="Alexandre Kojève" cert="high">Kojève</persName> (<date cert="low" from="1930" to="1939">1930s</date> and <date cert="low" from="1940" to="1949">1940s</date> <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/3017382">France</placeName>); <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95247377" sameAs="Theodor Adorno">Adorno</persName> and <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14771315" sameAs="Max Horkheimer" cert="high">Horkheimer</persName> (<date cert="low" from="1930" to="1939">1930s</date> to <date cert="low" from="1960" to="1969">1960s</date>, <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2921044">Germany</placeName>, <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6252001">United States</placeName>); <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/105151053" cert="high">Hannah Arendt</persName>, <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100236274">C. Wright Mills</persName>, <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/66467430" cert="high">Erich Fromm</persName>, <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/36921579">Herbert Marcuse</persName>, and others (<date cert="low" from="1950" to="1959">1950s</date> and <date to="1969" from="1960" cert="low">1960s</date>, United States) (<persName sameAs="Andrew Jamison" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/108305312">Jamison</persName> and <persName sameAs="Ron Eyerman" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/24681618" cert="high">Eyerman</persName> ch. 2); <persName sameAs="Guy Debord" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44297675">Debord</persName> and the Situationists ( <date to="1969" from="1960" cert="low">1960s</date>, France); <persName sameAs="Richard Hoggart" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/109123740">Hoggart</persName> and <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/68998327" cert="high">Stuart Hall</persName> (though modified; <date cert="low" from="1950" to="1959">1950s</date> to <date cert="low" from="1980" to="1989">1980s</date>, <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2635167" cert="high">Britain</placeName>); <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/108273432">Daniel Bell</persName>, <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/98486723">Judith Butler</persName>, and others (<date cert="low" from="1970" to="1979">1970s</date> to <date to="1999" from="1990" cert="low">1990s</date>, United States); <persName sameAs="Robin Blaser" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17240199" cert="high">Blaser</persName> and <persName sameAs="Frank Davey" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/5029235">Davey</persName> (<date to="1969" from="1960" cert="low">1960s</date> to <date to="1999" from="1990" cert="low">1990s</date>, <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6251999">Canada</placeName>); and <persName sameAs="Ariel Dorfman" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95177323">Dorfman</persName> (<date cert="low" from="1970" to="1979">1970s</date>, <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3895114" cert="high">Chile, Latin America</placeName>). In their apocalyptic narrative, culture is being overwhelmed and democracy distorted by the <q>mass culture</q> produced by agents of the dominant classes or <q>capital,</q> encoding their ideological, political, and economic interests in <q>products</q> to be decoded and passively internalized by <q>consumers</q> (Davey 16). Poststructuralists claimed to dispel texto-telepathism but actually occulted it, refashioning literarism in the interests of a cadre of academic <q>experts.</q><q>Reading in the classroom</q> (<persName cert="high" sameAs="Alec McHoul" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/2537401">McHoul</persName>), a highly specialized though diversified and conflicted kind of reading that is by no means paradigmatic, still dominates <q>literature</q> in academia and the upmarket media. It relies on the argument that, despite the <q>emancipation</q> from <q>dominant reading</q> (dominator’s reading) supposedly effected by <q>theory</q> (usually standing for [neo-Hegelian] <q>critical theory</q>), there remains a <q>preferred,</q> <q>exemplary,</q> or <q>resistant reading,</q> in fact usually the professor’s or professional critic’s reading.</ref>
                        </ref>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="p833">
                        <ref target="#historical_oppression">Social changes made elites and their <q>national</q> literatures more diverse, inclusive, self-critical, and contested while excluding most people and most reading and writing and while access to the <q>national</q> literature and arts remains restricted by factors from unequal education to cultural and social prejudice.</ref>
                        <ref target="#nationality_issue">
                            <ref target="#canon_formation">Construction of a Canadian literature was undertaken in earnest relatively late, after the <listEvent> <event> <label>Second World War</label> </event> </listEvent>, as (among other things) the response of Canadian elites and the institutions they dominated to greater demand for higher education, to increased immigration and social diversity, to exacerbated regional differences, and to the resulting perceived need for an ostensibly unifying and indigenous <q>national</q> culture to distinguish Canadian elites from others and from most Canadians, justifying their power and privileges. This culture, unlike LJ’s literary sources, could be neither popular and imported (mainly from the <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6252001">United States</placeName>) nor elite and imported (from <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2635167" cert="high">Britain</placeName>, <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/3017382">France</placeName>, and the United States).</ref>
                            <ref target="#critique_of_canon">Critique of such <q>national</q> literatures is under way but, like the organized institution of a Canadian literature, has been late reaching <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/6251999" cert="high">Canada</placeName>, and operates within a relatively closed world defended by versions of literarism. Canadian literature continues, with much government support, to write, publish, teach, archive, research, promote, and read what most Canadians don’t read or write and hardly know about (<persName sameAs="Frank Davey" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/5029235">Davey</persName> 101–02). Scholars and critics continue referring to the <q>influence</q> of Canadian literature on the <q>national consciousness</q> (among many, see <persName cert="high" sameAs="W.J. Keith" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32010086">Keith</persName> <date cert="high" when="2006">2006</date> 2:67), though, by a frequently cited criterion, a work of Canadian literature is a <q>bestseller</q> if it sells five thousand copies (<persName sameAs="Rebecca Wigod" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/104290343">Wigod</persName>; <persName sameAs="Diane Gedymin">Gedymin</persName> and <persName sameAs="Susan Driscoll" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/1799418" cert="high">Driscoll</persName> 42–43). Canadian media’s <q>bestseller</q> lists are rigged to reflect their targeted advertising demographic’s self-image (<persName sameAs="Scott MacDonald" cert="medium" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/106101861">MacDonald</persName>). <ref target="#economics">Accurate sales figures show that most Canadians’ reading originates outside Canada, isn’t written by Canadians or about Canada, and is similar to what most people read in the United States (174–77).</ref></ref>
                        </ref>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:id="p834"><ref target="#nationality_issue">As a necessary counterpart, Canadian literature largely ignores, disdains, mutilates, or occasionally appropriates what most Canadians read and write. Many Canadian writers with huge global sales are unknown to Canadian literature. Marshall (Margaret) Saunders’s international bestseller, <title level="m">Beautiful Joe</title> (<date when="1893" cert="high">1893</date>) with sales well over a million, and one of LJ’s favourite lifetime books, has received almost no attention from Canadian scholars and critics. <ref target="#archival_location">The late <persName cert="medium" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/71392045">Arthur Hailey</persName>, naturalized Canadian, praised by <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/110344377" cert="high">Robertson Davies</persName> and whose papers are deposited in the <placeName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/122308641">University of Toronto Library</placeName></ref> (<persName sameAs="John Shoesmith" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/305203136" cert="medium">Shoesmith</persName>), enjoyed world sales of 170 million; I found one study of his work by someone in Canadian literature. World sales of <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/8212381" cert="high">Janette Oke</persName>’s <q>inspirational romances</q> approach twenty-five million, but at a recent meeting of forty-odd literature professors, including <q>Canadianists,</q> in Oke’s home province of <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5883102">Alberta</placeName>, not one had heard of her, nor had the books-page editor of a major urban newspaper in the same province. <ref target="#violence">A few song lyrics by globally popular and respected Canadian artists such as <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/56703476" cert="high">Leonard Cohen</persName> and <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/85454013">Joni Mitchell</persName> are included in literature anthologies, severing words from music, text from performance and audience, in aesthetic violence and social disregard.</ref> <ref target="#intellectual_history">Until recently, on the rare occasions when Canadian literature considered what most Canadians read and write, alarmed disdain prevailed, as in the special issue on <q>Popular Culture</q> in <title level="j">Canadian Literature</title> (Spring <date cert="high" when="1986">1986</date>); though francophone scholars and critics showed both serious interest and more respect, as in the <date when="1982" cert="high">1982</date> issue of <title level="j"><hi xml:lang="fr-CA">Études littéraires</hi></title> on <q><hi xml:lang="fr-CA">La Consommation littéraire de masse au <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6325494">Québec</placeName>.</hi></q> <q>Book history,</q> print culture studies, <q>audience studies</q> (<persName sameAs="S.Elizabeth Bird" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/162462824" cert="high">Bird</persName>), daily-life poets and editors, and others have begun to loosen the neo-Hegelian hegemony, as chapters of the <title level="m">History of the Book in Canada</title> (<date cert="high" from="2004" to="2007">2004–2007</date>) and <persName sameAs="Tom Wayman" cert="medium" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/98293283">Wayman</persName>’s anthology <title level="m">Paperwork</title> demonstrate. But few in Canadian literature, and more recently cultural studies, take an interest in what most Canadians read, except when it can illustrate <q>massification</q> or be construed as <q>resistant</q> or <q>countercultural.</q> The few studies of the kind of poetry most Canadians write distinguished it as <q>folk poetry</q> from the <q>bardic</q> poetry and folksong of Romantic <q>national</q> cultures. This pioneering <date cert="low" from="1980" to="1989">1980s</date> work was outside Canadian literature and has since been far outstripped by research on oral, minority, marginal, or non-Western poetry that can be positively valorized within and in the interests of academia as <q>traditional,</q> <q>communitarian,</q> <q>resistant,</q> <q>countercultural,</q> and so on</ref></ref> (<persName sameAs="Maria Damon" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/43496891" cert="medium">Damon</persName> and <persName sameAs="Ira Livingstone" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/213192856" cert="high">Livingstone</persName>; <persName sameAs="Danielle Fuller" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/15049126">Fuller</persName>).</p>
                    <p xml:id="p835">Rejecting literarism enables us to understand literature as democratic art, not the writing and reading of a few, reflecting and promoting their interests and restricted to those able to afford prolonged special training, but the cultural right of all and the practice of many or most, with its own poetics and politics. <ref target="#critique_of_canon">Rejecting texto-telepathism enables us to understand Canadian literature as anything read or written by someone reading or writing as a Canadian, however defined.</ref> Against texto-telepathism, <persName sameAs="Roy Harris" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/41864503" cert="high">Harris</persName>’s <q>integrational linguistics</q> insists that communication is the active and collaborative creation of meanings in particular instances by and between people. And against literarism, <persName sameAs="Alec McHoul" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/2537401">McHoul</persName>’s <q>effective semiotics</q> (74–85) insists that meanings do not inhere in <q>texts</q> but are created by readers in instances that are always unique but equal. As LJ put it, <q type="block"> <l>We each must express in our own way</l> <l>The things that have happened from day to day.</l> </q></p>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head>Works Cited</head>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95247377">Adorno, Theodor</persName>, and <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/14771315">Max Horkheimer</persName>. <title level="m" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/181849136" cert="high">Dialectic of Enlightenment</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/124914324">Herder and Herder</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1972">1972</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/105151053" cert="high">Arendt, Hannah</persName>. <title level="m" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/204103423">The Origins of Totalitarianism</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/167837026" cert="high">Harcourt Brace</orgName>, <date when="1951" cert="high">1951</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/108273432">Bell, Daniel</persName>. <title level="m" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/307971574" cert="high">The Cultural Contradictions of Capitalism</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>: Basic Books, <date cert="high" when="1976">1976</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/162462824">Bird, S. Elizabeth</persName>. <title level="m">The Audience in Everyday Life: Living in a Media World</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/123500307">Routledge</orgName>, <date when="2003" cert="high">2003</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName>Blaser, Robin</persName>. <title level="a">The Recovery of the Public World.</title> <title level="m">Reflections on Cultural Policy: Past, Present and Future</title>. Ed. <persName>Evan Alderson</persName>, <persName>Robin Blaser</persName>, and <persName>Harold Coward</persName>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/6176823" cert="high">Waterloo, ON</placeName>: <orgName>Wilfrid Laurier UP</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1993">1993</date>. 17–38. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/85378455" cert="high">Bock, Jerry</persName>, <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/35790321">Larry Holofcener</persName>, and <persName>George David Wiess</persName>. <title level="a">Mr. Wonderful.</title> <date when="1956" cert="high">1956</date>. Song lyrics. <title level="s">AZLyrics</title>. Web. <date cert="high" when="2013-10-06">6 October 2013</date>.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/98486723" cert="high">Butler, Judith P</persName>. <title level="m" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/308000221">Subjects of Desire: Hegelian Reflections in Twentieth-Century France</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127175063" cert="high">Columbia UP</orgName>, <date when="1987" cert="high">1987</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/37200549">Corse, Sarah M.</persName> <title level="m">Nationalism and Literature: The Politics of Culture in <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/6251999" cert="high">Canada</placeName> and the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/6252001" cert="high">United States</placeName></title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2653941">Cambridge</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127979069" cert="high">Cambridge UP</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1997">1997</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/45965317">Crafts, Susan D.</persName>, <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/41042263" cert="high">Daniel Cavicchi</persName>, and <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/23336585">Charles Keil</persName>. <title level="m">My Music: Explorations of Music in Daily Life</title>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/4838633" cert="high">Middletown, CT</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/131639570">Wesleyan UP</orgName>, <date when="1993" cert="high">1993</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/43496891" cert="high">Damon, Maria</persName>, and <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/213192856">Ira Livingstone</persName>, eds. <title level="m">Poetry and Cultural Studies: A Reader</title>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/4914570" cert="high">Urbana</placeName>:<orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/122554477"> U of Illinois P</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="2009">2009</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/5029235" cert="medium">Davey, Frank</persName>. <title level="m">Reading Canadian Reading</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6183235">Winnipeg, MB</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/136390480" cert="high">Turnstone Press</orgName>, <date when="1988" cert="high">1988</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44297675">Debord, Guy</persName>. <title level="m"><hi xml:lang="fr-FR">La Société du spectacle; la théorie situationniste</hi></title>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2988507" cert="medium">Paris</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/126773634">Buchet/Chastel</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1971">1971</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95177323" cert="high">Dorfman, Ariel</persName>, and <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/34460281">Armand Mattelart</persName>. <title level="m">How to Read Donald Duck: Imperialist Ideology in the Disney Comic</title>. Trans. <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/92008540" cert="high">David Kunzle</persName>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>: International General, <date when="1971" cert="high">1971</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/34501210">Fleming, Patricia</persName>, and <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/273864527" cert="high">Yvan Lamonde</persName>, eds. <title level="m">History of the Book in Canada</title>, 3 vols. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6167865">Toronto</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/126595939" cert="high">U of Toronto P</orgName>, <date cert="high" from="2004" to="2007">2004–07</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/66467430">Fromm, Erich</persName>. <title level="m" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/177832430" cert="high">Escape from Freedom</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/267060317">Holt, Rinehart, and Winston</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1941">1941</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/15049126" cert="high">Fuller, Danielle</persName>. <title level="m">Writing the Everyday: Women’s Textual Communities in Atlantic Canada</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6077243">Montreal</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/5992500" cert="high">Kingston</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/141809819">McGill-Queen’s UP</orgName>, <date when="2004" cert="high">2004</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/108536033" cert="high">Garfinkel, Harold</persName>. <title level="m" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/306907310">Studies in Ethnomethodology</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/159368920" cert="high">Prentice-Hall</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1967">1967</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName>Gedymin, Diane</persName>, and <persName>Susan Driscoll</persName>. <title level="m">Get Published!: Professionally, Affordably, Fast</title>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/4254679" cert="high">Bloomington</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/277425225">iUniverse</orgName>, <date when="2010" cert="high">2010</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/108178108" cert="high">Giddens, Anthony</persName>. <title level="m" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/310265293">Modernity and Self-identity: Self and Society in the Late Modern Age</title>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2653941" cert="high">Cambridge</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/143396152">Polity Press</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1991">1991</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/18627631" cert="high">Greenhill, Pauline</persName>. <title level="m">True Poetry: Traditional and Popular Verse in Ontario</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/6077243">Montreal</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/5992500" cert="high">Kingston</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/141809819">McGill-Queen’s UP</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1989">1989</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/68998327">Hall, Stuart</persName>. <title level="m" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/314097461" cert="high">The Popular Arts</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2643743">London</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/144550791" cert="high">Hutchinson</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1964">1964</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/41864503">Harris, Roy</persName>. <title level="m" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/314387343" cert="high">Introduction to Integrational Linguistics</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2640729">Oxford</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/123753697" cert="high">Pergamon</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1998">1998</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/109123740">Hoggart, Richard</persName>. <title level="m" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/314328086" cert="high">The Uses of Literacy: Aspects of Working-class Life with Special Reference to Publications and Entertainments</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2643743">London</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/131167970">Chatto and Windus</orgName>, <date when="1957" cert="high">1957</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/108305312" cert="high">Jamison, Andrew</persName>, and <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/24681618">Ron Eyerman</persName>. <title level="m">Seeds of the Sixties</title>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/5327684" cert="high">Berkeley</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/148948307">U of California P</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1994">1994</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32010086" cert="high">Keith, W.J.</persName> <title level="m" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/307976793">Canadian Literature in English</title>. Rev. ed. Vol. 2. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/5949247" cert="high">Erin, ON</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/144183699">Porcupine’s Quill</orgName>, <date when="2006" cert="high">2006</date>.</bibl>
                            <bibl>---. <title level="m">An Independent Stance: Essays on English Canadian Criticism and Fiction</title>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/5949247" cert="high">Erin, ON</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/144183699">Porcupine’s Quill</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1991">1991</date>. Print. </bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/13017" cert="high">Kojève, Alexandre</persName>. <title level="m" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/199762862">Introduction à la lecture de Hegel: leçons sur </title>La Phénoménologie de l’esprit. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2988507" cert="high">Paris</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/159455390">Gallimard</orgName>, <date when="1947" cert="high">1947</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName>Longabucco, Matthew</persName>. <title level="a">Degrees of Difficulty: Modern American Poetry Explained and Unexplained.</title> Diss. <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/139712320" cert="high"><placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName> University</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="2009">2009</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/46764285">Lukács, Georg</persName>. <title level="m">History and Class Consciousness: Studies in Marxist Dialecticts</title>. Trans. <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/92073054" cert="high">Rodney Livingstone</persName>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/4931972">Cambridge, MA</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/159490691" cert="high">MIT Press</orgName>, <date when="1971" cert="high">1971</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName>MacDonald, Scott</persName>. <title level="a">The Dawn of a Bestseller Culture: The Advent of Accurate Sales Data Could Make <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/6251999" cert="high">Canada</placeName>’s Bestseller Lists Much Less Pretty.</title> <title level="m">Quill and Quire</title> (<date cert="high" when="2004-09">September 2004</date>): 4. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/36921579" cert="high">Marcuse, Herbert</persName>. <title level="m" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/309300835">One-dimensional Man: Studies in the Ideology of Advanced Industrial Society</title>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/4930956" cert="high">Boston</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/311352098">Beacon Press</orgName>, <date when="1964" cert="high">1964</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/2537401" cert="high">McHoul, Alec</persName>. <title level="m">Semiotic Investigations: Towards an Effective Semiotics</title>. <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/155098548">U of Nebraska P</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1996">1996</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100236274" cert="high">Mills, Charles Wright</persName>. <title level="m" cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/314021965">White Collar: The American Middle Classes</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/140705396" cert="high">Oxford UP</orgName>, <date when="1951" cert="high">1951</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/103982524">Renwick, Roger deV</persName>. <title level="m" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/314622327" cert="high">English Folk Poetry: Structure and Meaning</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/4560349">Philadelphia</placeName>: <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/159571939" cert="high">U of Pennsylvania P</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1980">1980</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/117385338">Robson, Catherine</persName>. <title level="m">Heart Beats: Everyday Life and the Memorized Poem</title>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/5102922" cert="high">Princeton, NJ</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/158317684">Princeton UP</orgName>, <date when="2012" cert="high">2012</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/300128244" cert="high">Shoesmith, John</persName>. <title level="a">Arthur Hailey.</title> <title level="m">The Halcyon: The Newsletter of the Friends of the Thomas Fisher Rare Book Library</title> 45 (<date cert="high" when="2010-06">June 2010</date>): 3–4. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95207986">Stevenson, Robert Louis</persName>. <title level="m" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/313905874" cert="high">A Child’s Garden of Verses</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2643743">London</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127267947">Longmans, Green</orgName>, <date when="1885" cert="high">1885</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9107221" cert="high">Walker, Cindy</persName>, and <persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/32182471">Eddy Arnold</persName>. <title level="a">You Don’t Know Me.</title> <date cert="high" when="1955">1955</date>. Song lyrics. <title level="m">Metrolyrics</title>. Web. <date when="2013-10-06" cert="high">6 October 2013</date>.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/104290343" cert="high">Wigod, Rebecca</persName>. <title level="a">What Does It Take to Be a Bestseller?</title> <title level="m">Vancouver Sun</title>, <date cert="high" when="2007-02-17">17 February 2007</date>. Web.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/98293283">Wayman, Tom</persName>. <title level="m">Paperwork: Contemporary Poems from the Job</title>. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/6173331" cert="high">Vancouver</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/267065038">Harbour Publishing</orgName>, <date when="1991" cert="high">1991</date>. Print.</bibl>
                            <bibl><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12428950" cert="high">Woodmansee, Martha</persName>. <title level="m">The Author, Art, and the Market: Rereading the History of Aesthetics</title>. <placeName cert="high" ref="http://www.geonames.org/5128581">New York</placeName>: <orgName cert="high" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127175063">Columbia UP</orgName>, <date cert="high" when="1994">1994</date>. Print.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </div>
                </div>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
        

    </text>
</TEI>